leading to his first paper, which is affiliated with the Department of Genetics here at UGA.
The Green Lab develops machine learning methods to integrate disparate large-scale datasets,
develops deep learning methods for extracting contacts from these datasets, and then brings
these capabilities to molecular biologists through open and transparent science.
Of particular note to folks interested in large language models, like CHAT-GPT, Dr.
Green and others recently posted a preprint on how AI might be able to help us write and
revise our academic manuscripts.
Please join me in welcoming Dr. Casey Green to UGA.
Okay, thank you, yeah, it's good to be back.
I actually spent a summer working in this building in the Department of Genetics.
Everything around this building looks different now, but somehow the building still looks
the same.
I'm excited to get a chance to share some of what we've been doing in our group and
then to share some of what's going on at the University of Colorado and sort of give you
an idea of what the ecosystem is like where we are.
I think it's always important to think about kind of what our role as informaticists in
science is, like what do we bring to the ecosystem, and I like to think of what we contribute
as essentially serendipity, right?
If we do our jobs well, people will see something in their data that they hadn't seen before,
and they will make a different decision based on that.
So I like to, you know, think about how we can make more kind of serendipitous moments.
I'll start with a brief vignette of a project that we started quite a few years ago now
trying to understand rare diseases.
And in particular, what factors might drive a rare, what systemic factors might drive
a rare disease.
The world when we started this project was one where looking across multiple data sets
remained somewhat challenging.
It's time consuming, you have to deal with batch and technical artifacts.
And so our question when we started, a postdoc joined the lab and the idea was, well, you
know, here's the gap that we're facing.
If you want to analyze multiple data sets at the same time, to identify systemic factors,
that means you're looking at different tissues, probably looking at different cohorts, there's
potentially different disease contexts, might be different controls.
All of this makes your life a lot harder, you can't just kind of make an assumption
that you're going to do three different t tests and be done with it.
And so what this postdoc wanted to do was say, okay, can I find these commonalities
without it taking an inordinately large amount of time.
And she was very interested in not taking an inordinately large amount of time because
the strategy that she used in her PhD, before she joined the group, was developed, she developed
this approach using a modular framework to analyze these data sets, where you essentially
take different data sets, decompose them into modules, and then try to map a module in one
data set to a module in another data set to a module in another data set.
This is possible, if you're an expert in the disease, and you're an expert in all the tissues
that sort of are affected, you can do this, you can say, okay, this is this pathway response
in this tissue, and this is this other pathway response in this other tissue, but it's really
time consuming.
And the complexity grows essentially, with at least the square of the number of modules
that you want to look at.
So you sort of restrict yourself to a modest number of modules if you want to do this in
any practical amount of time.
There are potentially ways to automate this, you know, using over representation analysis
or other strategies to try to, you know, make life easier on the mapping stage, so you don't
spend a lot of time looking at stuff that's unlikely to be fruitful.
But either way, it's challenging, it takes a bunch of time and it requires a lot of expertise.
So what Dr. Jacqueline Tironi did was say, well, what I really want is a module library,
like how could this process or cell type be represented in any data set that I look at,
I'd like to be able to pull that off the shelf, and then take that module library to different
data sets, and then look at each of those data sets in terms of those modules and just
look directly across those modules.
I don't have to now sort of do the module connection after the fact, I can do it upfront.
This would be great, wouldn't it be great if.
And so her hypothesis was that, you know, these modules don't just exist in one data
set, they exist across human biology.
So could she, so her hypothesis was that she would be able to learn these reusable modules
by taking many, many, many different data sets, decomposing those different data sets
into modules, and then sort of learning which modules were necessary to reconstruct the
original data.
And then once she did that, she could do that on a generic collection of data, and then
hopefully be able to use that on her data sets of interest.
And in this case, we're interested in studying a disease called Enka-associated vasculitis,
which is rare enough that if you look at large collections of public RNA-seq data, you don't
find it.
So it's quite a rare disease.
So the idea here was, if she took a whole bunch of generic samples, essentially random
human data that she downloaded from the internet, transcriptomic data, she decomposed that,
she could decompose that into patterns, and then she could take those patterns and we
could apply those to the rare disease data sets of interest, and potentially do sort
of standard statistics with that.
We, just to give you an idea of the data set that we started with, so this is a data set
ReCount 2, I think there's now a ReCount 3.
This is produced by Jeff Leak's group at Hopkins.
And if you wanted 70,000 RNA-seq samples, you can just get 70,000 uniformly processed
RNA-seq samples.
What I like to tell Jackie is that her project had to be successful, because if you think
about the resources we were giving her to start it, if you just benchmark that those
samples probably cost about $1,000 to generate, you know, I like to tell her, look, we gave
you $70 million to start your project, you have to do something with $70 million, right?
So, this was the data that we used, and then we tried quite a few different methods to
extract patterns, including some that we developed in our group, but we ended up coming to this
method called PLYR, which is from Maria Shakina's group at Pitt.
And PLYR is the Pathway-Level Information Extractor, and it does a couple things that
are really nice.
So, it's essentially doing this matrix decomposition, but as you do the matrix decomposition, there's
a couple sort of regularization factors and some penalties in it, and essentially, it
has some sparsity properties that we really like, so the idea is that you want to be able
to explain a dataset with relatively few latent variables.
Also, you want your latent variables to have only a modest number of genes in them.
And finally, if those latent variables can align with a pathway, you'd really prefer
that the latent variable align with a pathway, because anytime you're doing this decomposition,
you're essentially doing some arbitrary rotation, right?
PCA is essentially learning an arbitrary, it's learning a rotation of your data, a reduced
dimension space rotation of your data.
The rotation in PCA is essentially arbitrary, I mean, you've chosen that you want to maximize
the variance on the first axis, but you could have chosen anything else, like ICA, you're
just like, I don't care, just make it small.
So in this case, what it's doing is it's essentially saying, if a pathway can line up with an axis,
let's do that.
And so it's a little bit less, that's the intuition for what it's doing, it's actually
a little bit, the regularization is a little bit different than that.
And what that gives you is a really nice level of interpretability.
So instead of having to think about a module as, like, instead of saying, okay, this cell
type is, these three different axes of variability added in some fraction, usually those cell
types are going to come out as a single axis in your data.
So it makes it much more easy to think through and reason about the solutions.
And so what we essentially did is say, okay, well, we have this enormous collection of
generic human data from the internet, ReCount2, and we have a plier, and we'd like that to
be a machine learning model that we could use in many different biological contexts.
So we named it multi-dataset plier, but because in bioinformatics, everything has to have
a name, we just shortened that to multiplier.
And so this is kind of a multiplier idea.
I'm just going to give you a couple highlight results from the paper that I think help to
kind of give an idea of why you might want to do this.
The paper is pretty exhaustive.
It has a significant deep dive into sort of exactly what's happening in this stuff, but
I'll just give you kind of the high points.
Essentially what we wanted to understand is, does this model learn something we didn't
already know?
And is it better than if you just took data from the disease of interest?
We couldn't get enough data from the disease of interest, which is psychosociative vasculitis.
So we did that analysis in the paper, and we just didn't learn many axes of variability
because there's too little data.
So what we wanted to do is say, well, let's pick something where we could actually learn
something.
Let's sort of give this idea a chance.
And then we said, well, let's imagine we're studying a different autoimmune disease, lupus.
So that's what's here, where it says SLE, this box plot.
What we've done is we've collected all the whole blood data that we could get from individuals
with lupus that was publicly available to create one collection of data.
Then what we've done with RECOUNT2, which is the generic human data from the internet,
is we've taken RECOUNT2 and we've subsampled it to be the same size as the lupus set.
So that's the box plot.
The box plot is RECOUNT2 subsampled.
And then where you see the diamond, that's what happens if you just take the complete
collection of data from RECOUNT2.
Okay, so let's label our X.
Oh, so yeah, so these data sets, if you think about the science behind this, this experiment
has these two data sets of the same size, but different composition.
These two are the same composition of the data, but they're quite different sizes.
I think 70 times larger for the diamond than the other.
And so then we can ask, okay, so how many patterns are we learning from our data?
So this method uses the latent variable decomposition, so the number of latent variables, which are
essentially patterns.
You can see that if you want to learn more patterns, there's sort of more, and there's
a heuristic and plier for sort of selecting the optimal number of latent variables, and
we use that heuristic here, it seems like a pretty reasonable heuristic.
It uses cross-validation to essentially ask how frequently you're rediscovering the same
latent variables.
So if you do that, you find that you can learn more latent variables or recurrent patterns
in the data if you have less heterogeneity in your data given a fixed sample size.
I don't think this is going to shock anyone, right?
If I give you a limited amount of data, you would like that data to be as consistent as
possible except for the thing you'd like to vary, right?
That's usually a good place to live.
So that's what we see here, right?
You get more latent variables out of the lupus data than the subsampled recount2 data, but
if I told you, well, you can have really messy data, but you can have a lot of it, now you
can learn a lot more patterns.
So you end up with many fold more patterns that you can learn, the kind of recurrent
patterns across the data set if you have more data.
So you'd rather have less heterogeneity, but sometimes having more samples can overcome
the heterogeneity issue.
So that's the first thing we ask.
So you get kind of more total patterns.
The next thing we can ask is, okay, well, we don't know what complete collection of
processes are transcriptionally co-regulated, right?
This is not something we know a priori.
We can get a collection of processes if we go to Gene Ontology or KEGG or other databases,
but some of those may not be transcriptionally co-regulated.
However, if we're seeing a process that's coming out as transcriptionally co-regulated,
that's probably a positive hit.
And so that's kind of the assumption we're making here.
So this is looking at both the SLE and the ReCount2 data again.
This axis is what fraction of the pathways that we know about are coming back as sort
of aligned with one or more axes in the data.
And so you can see this actually wasn't driven by composition of the data, this was driven
by sample size.
So if you put in more data, you can learn kind of more transcriptional co-regulation.
This obscures a little bit of what's going on here because the processes are a little
bit different.
If you look at what happens in the ReCount2 data, you end up learning, as you get to the
large sample size, you end up learning more granular processes.
So it seems like it's probably that you're covering the same things that are transcriptionally
co-regulated, you just get a higher level of resolution.
And then, so you kind of learn more of the stuff we know we should know about.
So at this point, anything I'm showing you, you could also do with GSEA or any of these
other methods, gene set enrichment analysis, or those types of methods.
But we can also ask, can we learn anything we didn't already know going in?
So this is asking what fraction of the latent variables that are coming back are not associated
with the pathway.
And what you can see is, when you have the sort of more modest sample sizes, about half
of the latent variables that come back were associated with the pathway, and the other
half are potentially novel.
Could be novel biology, it could be a technical artifact.
What you see when you get the large collection of ReCount2 data is, you know, that number
drops to about 20%.
So 80% of the latent variables that are coming back didn't exist in the databases that we
had available to us going into it.
So that's a really nice thing to have in your back pocket if you want to say, well, look,
I want to explore the biology of what's going on in this disease, but I don't want to limit
myself to what people have curated into a database.
So this is kind of a data-driven way to figure out what those modules could be.
And you might also say, well, there's probably just an enormous amount of technical artifacts.
You just told me you gathered a whole bunch of random human data from the internet.
One of the positive things that we saw that was kind of suggestive that this is not driven
exclusively by technical artifacts is actually this proportion bumps up a little bit when
you look at the ReCount2 data, as opposed to the SLE data.
If it was entirely driven by technical artifacts, you'd actually expect this to have fewer latent
variables that were associated only with a known process.
So this was also encouraging.
So this gives us the idea that we kind of learn more unknown unknowns.
And then there's quite a bit more of a deep dive in the paper, like looking at sort of
one of the things that we see is instead of having a cell cycle latent variable, you end
up with different phases of the cell cycle partitioned into latent variables.
But the sort of takeaway was that if you do these machine learning analyses while reusing
data from other contexts, you can get this level of detail that you couldn't get just
analyzing your data alone.
So starting with a whole bunch of other data, learning the pathways and processes there,
and then applying it to your data gives you this higher level of resolution.
There is a bit of an implicit assumption here, which is if the process that you were looking
at is truly unique and only occurs in your setting and no other settings, you can't find
it because it's not going to be present in the variability from other people's data.
I think this is probably rare.
I don't think it's terribly common that there are processes that are so exclusive that they're
only used in one and only one biological context and nowhere else.
But if you believe that to be the case, you should know you will not find it with this
method.
And so then just kind of recapitulating.
So in the past, when Jackie joined the group, she had this modular framework approach, which
is actually really nice and is now used, it's been used in scleroderma and other contexts
to connect pathways across tissues and studies.
But the multiplier approach she developed has some nice advantages.
So she takes this generic human data, recount two, she can train a model, then transfer
it to the datasets of interest, and then just look across those datasets with standard statistics.
So this is an example of one of the things we can do with this.
So this was actually the thing we wanted to do when we started the study.
So these are three different datasets from individuals with ANCA-associated vasculitis.
One of the challenges here is that all of these datasets are microarray-based.
All of our training data is RNA-seq.
A different student in the lab developed a technique to do, if you're interested in taking
sort of machine learning methods and applying them to gene expression data across these
contexts, for many methods, there's reasonable ways to do that transformation that is not
completely horrendous, which is the best advertisement I can get for a method.
But there's quite a few different methods.
And actually, quantile normalization is not bad in this context.
The zeros kind of give you a bit of trouble, but it's not horrendous.
And so this is what we're doing here.
So we're actually asking, can the multiplier model actually apply to array datasets, even
though it's trained exclusively in RNA-seq data?
We would have done this in RNA-seq data, but it turned out there wasn't RNA-seq data for
this that was available yet.
So now we've gotten to the point where the datasets for this disease are large enough
that they actually do exist in RNA-seq as well.
So what's going on here?
So we've got three different datasets, airway epithelial cells, renal glomeruli, and PPMCs.
They're collected in three different studies, so there's no matched people.
And also the conditions are brutally different.
So what's going to happen is from the left side to the right side of each of these plots,
we're going to go from the least, from the most severe form of the disease to sort of
the least severe form of the disease for healthy controls.
So this dataset for the airway epithelial cells has, these are the vasculitis data,
but then it's got things like pancreatic rhinitis, healthy.
And so we're basically saying, okay, what is associated with severity across these three
different cohorts?
And so one of the latent variables that comes up as a severity associated is this M0 macrophage
signature.
And you can see the same thing where in each group you look in, the least severe form of
the disease is on the right, the more severe form of the disease is on the left.
So you can see this latent variable severity associated due to the bizarre sort of path
of academic publishing.
So our guess was that M0 macrophages could be involved here.
Well, before this actually was published, but after the preprint came out, we had some
follow-up work.
And I have to break all the chronology of science.
Our follow-up work came out first demonstrating that it looked like there was a change in
macrophage metabolism in the disease that could be sort of influencing severity in a
systemic way.
You can also use this type of analysis to say what's particular to a tissue, right?
So you could say what latent variables are associated with severity in this tissue, but
not other tissues.
So it gives you the ability to start doing those analyses in a way that it's pretty darn
difficult to do with just the modular framework alone.
And then I have an almost five-year-old, she turns five in three weeks, and she's been
watching Zootopia.
And there's a line in a song in Zootopia where I was listening, I'm like, oh my gosh, this
is science.
So the line is, I'll keep on making those new mistakes.
I'll keep on making them every day, those new mistakes.
And so we're really big on this in the lab, right?
But what I tell people is, it's not going to work, just make it not work differently
each time.
If it's not working the same way each time, that's not good, but if it's not working for
different reasons, that's perfect.
And so we do this in our own work.
So this is the first part of the GitHub that's rate me that's associated with this paper.
So if you want to know sort of, these are all notebooks, if you want to follow along
with the work that we did for this multiplier paper.
The first part of this is kind of our proof of concept exploration to just understand
how the method worked.
Then you get to the stuff that's in the paper, then you get to the stuff that's in the supplement,
then you get to the stuff that's neither in the paper nor the supplement, because it turned
out the paper was too long.
And so this gives you a way to see like, okay, here's all the stuff we did.
So there was one experiment that we did where we wanted to say, can you predict outcome
in clinical trials from these latent variables?
And so we got this Rituximab data set from the NIH that was testing this.
It turned out that the data set structure was, let's say, suboptimal, in that some of
it was paired end and some of it was not paired end sequencing.
And this was confounded with the endpoint.
So it turned out to be extremely difficult to analyze, and we couldn't really learn anything
from it.
But if you're interested in using that for your own work, probably not that data set,
that idea.
You know, we've got a notebook here that's like, okay, here was our attempt to build
a model to predict response.
So you can start from that.
So if you're interested in this, we try to do this for each of our papers.
So this is available.
The GitHub is here.
If you search for Taroni and multiplier, you'll probably find it.
But I thought this was a nice example of kind of how we've taken a project from inception
through execution through kind of deliverables.
This method, we've seen some other uses now.
So someone used the same thing to study neurofibromatosis.
That came out relatively recently.
I can't remember, there's a few other sort of rare disease analyses that people have
started using this for.
But we really like seeing that, right?
Because it demonstrates uptake that is in a, I mean, rare disease transcriptomics is
a relatively small community.
So it's nice to see this stuff beginning to catch on.
I would also say, you know, we started with about $70 million worth of data.
If you are Lego Grace Hopper and you happen to have an internet connection, you can have
about $4 billion worth of data at your fingertips.
So if you're interested, there's a few more resources that have come online.
I think Arches 4 now has like 650,000 samples.
So that's about, you know, if you want to estimate $650 million of preprocessed data
at your fingertips.
In a previous position, we built something called Refined Bio that's about a million
samples.
So these types of resources are available, which is great, because then you don't have
to go back and rebuild this.
You don't have to do all the software engineering to reprocess the data in a uniform way.
You just kind of start from the processed data.
And I think this opens up a lot of avenues of exploration.
I like to, you know, one of the things that I say about what our lab works on is machine
learning, public data, and the transcriptome.
Pick two of three, and we're probably interested.
One of our Bush essentially wrote and designed the way that we fund science in this country.
So this idea that most science is going to happen outside of government research labs,
it's mostly going to happen at universities, it's mostly going to be grant funded.
He wrote this letter to FDR that says, the pioneer spirit is still vigorous within this
nation science offers a largely unexplored hinterland for the pioneer who has the tools
for his task.
Well, I would say, I think open data is like the opportunities here are remarkable, like
the ability to, you can take these data sets off the shelf and learn how something works
at a scale that's very difficult to do from the data generated in only one lab.
And once you do that, you can then test it.
And I think I really think using other people's data as sort of the starting point to generate
hypotheses that you then go test.
There's an enormous amount of unexplored opportunity here.
We also think sometimes about other data types instead of just gene expression.
So this is work from David Nicholson, who was a PhD student in the lab who just graduated
last year, who was like, well, let's do that.
I just want to understand what's on bioRxiv anyway.
So at this point, I probably don't have to introduce it, bioRxiv is a preprint server.
And so this gives us the ability to also study the peer review process in some ways.
So we can see what gets posted to bioRxiv, and then we can look at the sort of what the
final paper looks like.
We started this project just around the time that bioRxiv released an XML repository of
their complete collection of data.
So if you're interested in not just having a complete collection of transcriptomic data,
you can also go get a complete collection of XML preprints, which I think is really
exciting and a lot of fun.
You learn some things if you start looking at just the metadata associated with this.
So this is one of the simple questions that David asked was just, well, if there are preprints
with multiple versions, are people sort of adjusting their preprint in response to peer
review?
So if someone submits their paper, they get comments back, do they generally repost it?
We can't directly answer that question, we don't have access to the journal system.
But we could say as well, if that were happening, probably what would happen is that at each,
you know, as you saw in each version, you'd see an extension in the time to publish.
Sure enough, you see that.
And actually, the coefficient on the X here is about 50, which is in days.
So it suggests that adding a version means sort of 50 days longer in the publication
process, which is kind of aligned with what you'd expect to see if people are putting
up papers and revising them in response to peer review.
Another thing we can ask, so this is getting into the text itself, is if the text changes,
do more changes in text between the preprint and the published version result in, does
that come with a longer time to publish?
And the answer to that is kind of yes-ish.
If a preprint changes more from the, if a published version changes more from the preprint,
it does take a bit longer to publish.
But it's not an incredibly substantial change.
And actually, the other thing that we did, so as we were doing this project, there was
another group that did a completely different project, where they took a set of COVID papers
that were published first as preprints and followed them through.
Their scientific question was different.
They wanted to say, for COVID-related papers, does the message of the paper change as it
goes through the publication process?
And they found that only in one case did that happen out of the 300-odd papers that they
examined.
But what that gave us was an annotated list of COVID papers.
So we could then take that and ask if it had the same relationship, and it actually didn't
have the same relationship.
So for the subset of the literature in early 2020, COVID papers were being published quickly
regardless of how much text changed between the preprint and published version.
So this was kind of an interesting way to explore how publishing was happening.
So for those of you who have had the opportunity to have papers go through peer review, can
you guess what the most common linguistic change is, if we just look at word-level linguistic
change during the publishing process?
Has anyone ever had to add supplementary or additional data?
It's not the most common.
The most common is actually, oh, no, it is the most common, yeah.
So additional and file.
So on the right here is what's enriched in the published literature, and the left is
what's enriched in preprints.
So file and additional and supplementary are all pretty high at the top.
So when people are changing their papers, we can infer that probably they're often changing
the, you know, they're adding stuff to the supplement, but maybe they're not adding that
much to the main paper.
The other stuff that's in there is kind of interesting, like fig and figure.
So because journals have different styles, the plus-minus symbol and the em dash.
So you can see the artifacts of typesetting, but this gives a way to kind of understand
what's on each side.
And this, I should say, we've done this, so this analysis is using only preprint published
pairs.
If you do the same thing with all of BioRxiv and all of PubMed, you essentially find field
differences.
So some fields use BioRxiv more than others.
So this is the more carefully controlled than that.
The other thing that we've done, just if you happen to have a preprint yourself, we have
this web server that does a linguistic comparison between a selected preprint and all of PubMed
and says, okay, well, here's journals that publish linguistically similar papers.
Here's papers that are linguistically similar to yours, and this has a secret feature.
So what we encourage people to do, and we designed it to try to get people to upload
their preprint, but then people are like, well, I have a preprint, but it's on archive
and you don't support archive.
So the secret feature, which you can also drag a PDF over the search box if you want
to, but we don't generally advertise that because the goal was to get people to post
preprints so they could use the service, but we don't support archive.
So if you have an archive preprint, we'll allow you to put, to drag it over the search
box, but no other PDFs.
So this came out last year, and there's, again, a GitHub associated with it if you want to
see all the kind of exploration that we did on the way.
David had a follow-up paper that I'm really excited about where he looked at, he looked
at the, what words change their meaning over time, and in the last 20 years of scientific
publishing.
So there's an application associated with that as well that I should have put the link
on here, but didn't, that we call WordLabs.
So if you go to our lab and look for WordLabs, you'll find that, and it's really interesting.
So we see things like hallmarks of new technologies, like, you know, CRISPR has a linguistic shift.
We also see a lot of pandemic-associated words have linguistic shifts.
So if you're interested in understanding how our language changes, that's also something
that David did.
Okay, and then I know this is a less medically-related audience than most of the places that I speak,
but one of the things that I thought I wanted to share was sort of how some of this basic
science or sort of the techniques that we develop in this basic science can contribute
to changes in how healthcare gets delivered.
And so this is also something that we think about, right?
Remember our business is serendipity.
Yes, sometimes that's in research, right?
Whether that's sort of me telling you how papers change, so that you can think about
how you would change your paper in response to peer review, just add more additional files.
But sometimes that's, you know, in care, in clinical care, right?
So that someone, you know, you can imagine a patient comes in, there might be reasons
that that patient might need to receive a different treatment.
Could we provide that kind of information at the point of care?
So this is a big focus at our med school and our health system that's associated with our
med school, University of Colorado Health, has an entire program in clinical intelligence.
This is sort of the idea that I like to highlight as sort of serendipity is like the right moment
at the right time to make the right decision.
In most health systems, if someone is going to get something called pharmacogenomic genetic
testing.
So the idea here is people have different variants in their genome.
Some of those variants can affect how you metabolize drugs, how you respond to different
drugs.
It's not terribly common that people get tested for pharmacogenomic variants, because if you
go get, if you are going to a hospital and, you know, you need to have a stent inserted,
one of the common treatments is Plavix, well, there's a, there's an interaction between
Plavix and a certain genetic variant, a set of genetic variants where you metabolize the
drug differently, and it doesn't work for you, which means you're not getting the benefit
of reducing your heart attack risk, or your clot risk.
And so, but most people don't get this testing, because if a physician orders the testing,
they get a 70 page PDF back, then they have to take that 70 page PDF and go to a table
like this, read everything related to the drug they're about to prescribe, to prescribe
on the table, and then understand if it applies, right?
That is not a common thing for a physician to do.
Providers don't get reimbursed for that type of type of work.
What's happening at the University of Colorado and UC Health is we've got clinical decision
support built into the electronic health record around this stuff.
So this is the same thing, except instead of a 70 page PDF, plus having to look at this
table, if a provider were to go in and order Plavix for an individual who's not going to
benefit from it, it pops up an alert that says, look, we recommend you remove this because
it's not going to work, and read about why it's not going to work if you want to, but
we recommend you apply one of these alternatives that will work for this patient.
And so this is serendipity, but not just in research, in clinical care.
And this is, if you're interested in this kind of story, this is another one.
This was an individual, different condition, where there was a question about drug efficacy.
This is a story from UC Health.
And in this case, the provider keyed in an order, and an alert popped up that says, oh,
this person's going to need a different dose.
And that was helpful to the provider to make that decision.
One of the things I've had the privilege of doing over the last couple of years is focusing
on this program.
So a lot of faculty in our department work in this program, and about a year and a half
ago, I guess two years ago, the previous director left, and so I ended up as the interim director.
So I've gotten to know this program pretty well.
So this is our Colorado Center for Personalized Medicine.
We have a biobank study that this is all tied to.
So if someone comes in, they can consent to have their sample collected for the biobank.
We have a robust return of results pipeline built on that.
So our biobank is growing pretty rapidly.
Our sample increase is picking up a lot.
But then the other thing we ask is, how is this making a difference in care?
So essentially, how many of these alerts are actually firing?
So over the last year, we've had about 1,000 patients who've had an alert fire at some
point in clinical care.
That's a tenfold increase over our entire previous history.
And that's been powered because we've recently focused on getting these results back into
the EHR in a structured way.
So we've seen almost 100-fold growth, actually more than 100-fold growth year over year.
We'll probably have 210,000 results in the electronic health record at sort of the two-year
mark.
And what this means is that if you're interested in studying this type of process in terms
of care delivery, if you're interested in studying how physicians respond, if you're
interested in looking for new cases where there are these sort of drug-gene interactions,
we have the ingredients to do that at Colorado in a way that no one else that I'm aware of
does.
And so this program continues to grow.
I'll just give you one.
This is actually a real story that happened over the last few months.
So this is a stock photo.
I cannot show you a picture of the patient, but a patient came in to a community oncology
clinic.
And this works across the entire UC health system.
So it's not just an academic hospital.
This is a major health system that serves the Mountain West.
So this patient came into a community oncology clinic.
They were prescribed a drug that based on their genetic variants would have created
a significant risk of life-threatening complications.
Our team noticed this, sent a message to the provider, and then the patient alert actually
fired and recommended a reduced dosage of the drug.
The oncologist actually did proactively reduce the dose.
So the person started at a different dose than would traditionally be used.
Even at that dose, they didn't tolerate it very well.
So they had to further reduce the dose.
In these types of cases, you can imagine what happens if you start at the highest sort of
the traditional dose at which these drugs can be for individuals with this particular
variant can be lethal.
And so this is a case where, you know, yes, I told you there's 1,000 alerts, but each
of those 1,000 alerts is some story like this, right?
And so it's nice to see this actually being used to deliver care at scale.
And so we're doing this, this is all informatics, right?
You can get all of this serendipity with sort of none of this here has machine learning
built into it, but it's going to.
And as we think about that, I think it's really important not just to sort of think
from the machine learning point of view, but to really think about practical clinical care
pathways.
So this is a piece from Siddhartha Mukherjee that sort of, if you're interested in AI and
medicine, I realize this is dated now, but it's still worth reading.
And it's also weird that five years is old, but it's still worth reading.
It has a quote from Geoffrey Hinton, sort of says they should stop training radiologists
right now.
And why would someone say this, right?
Well, so Geoff Hinton's looking at the literature, right?
So they're just trying to collect some literature from around the same time.
So this is sort of saying, look, deep learning is going to completely transform healthcare.
It's going to change how we care as we know it.
Another sort of similar example, more examples, everything you read in the literature, deep
learning.
Like, I mean, now we're all into large language models, but at the time these image models
were going to completely transform healthcare.
Well, you might ask, is there anything they're not good at?
Like they're good at everything, right?
Chihuahuas and blueberry muffins, not terribly good here.
This one's kind of wild.
So I perceive the thing on the left as a panda.
It looks like a picture of a panda.
I don't really perceive this as much of anything.
We're going to add, you know, this plus seven thousandths of this.
What do you think the output is going to look like?
A sloth.
A sloth?
Any Gibbons?
Anyone for Gibbon?
A bear.
A bear?
Okay.
So this is what it looks like.
It's a Gibbon.
Clearly a Gibbon.
No question.
That's a Gibbon.
A monkey.
Okay.
So it doesn't look like a Gibbon to me, but our neural network is exceedingly convinced.
And the reason this works, right, is because the decision boundaries in these neural networks
are sort of nonlinear, and you can end up pretty close to a decision boundary without
really knowing it.
This is another example, which I think is just a lot of fun, so I have to throw it in.
So this is someone who was like, well, can I just make adversarial, like, sticker?
Like, can I have a sticker that I can put on something and have a deep neural network
perceive it as something, even if it's not?
So this is the toaster sticker.
And so you can give, you can put the toaster sticker on a table next to what I perceive
to be a, I perceive this to be a toaster sticker on a table next to a banana.
I perceive this to be a banana on a table.
Neural network classifier, banana on a table.
It's good.
Stick the toaster sticker next to it?
Absolutely a toaster.
You can imagine doing the same things with stop signs, you can imagine doing the same
things with other fun technologies in the world of self-driving cars or deep neural
networks or vision.
Okay, so let's go back to the automated radiologist finding pneumonia.
This was one of the examples I showed you before.
There's a, John Zek is a guy who writes blog posts that are really good and then converts
them into papers.
So this was a blog post from John Zek, which then became a paper that sort of said, okay,
why is the system actually working?
Like what's happening here?
So he went to the, to the images and tried to understand, you know, what part of the
image is contributing to the prediction of pneumonia?
Well in this case, a positive, and this should probably find pneumonia.
There's high density in the lung here.
You can say, well, okay.
Oh, and I should say a positive number is suggestive of pneumonia, a negative number
is not.
Okay.
So what are the positive numbers?
The most positive numbers, bottom, yeah, where there's this interesting stripe, the interesting
stripe that's kind of unique characteristic of the scanner, the one that you might see
if you were in a department, if the scanner was placed proximal to sort of where pneumonia
diagnoses were usually occurring.
Yeah.
So, so, so that's interesting.
Here's another one.
I should say these probabilities are low, but the previous one was in the 99th percentile
for pneumonia.
This one's in the 95th percentile.
Yeah.
Portable?
Portable.
Someone's not well enough to go to the scanner.
Not a good sign for their health, could indicate pneumonia.
Probably not the part of the image you want to be looking at.
And so, you know, I think this to me, I was also reading this every once in a while, I
read the comment section of blog posts on the internet, which I do not recommend, but
there was one on big data.
You know, there was this blog post on big data and I'm like, well, it was like why statistics
don't matter in the era of big data or something like that.
And I'm like, okay, I'll, you know, and then I'm like, I have some disagreements with this.
Then I go to the comment section, I find this one, which I really agree with.
On big data, data collection biases are always larger than statistical uncertainty.
And I think this is why I sort of, you know, you can have these models that perform robustly
around a lot of these comparisons that still struggle.
And then I read, who made the post, and it's this guy named Daniel Himmelstein, which probably
doesn't mean anything to you, but he happened to be a postdoc in my lab.
And I'm like, dude, put this in the comment section of the internet, people should actually
read it.
So now I put it on slides, so at least someone can see it.
Okay, so how do we design systems that work?
So you know, for AI and medicine, regardless of what we're using, I think we need to have
some principles that we think about.
We just did something that sort of tries to go on this path.
So this is a little bit different.
So this is a piece from Nature, but it talks about a preprint that we put up earlier this
year, where we were trying to use GPT-based models, so in this case, GPT-3, to revise
academic manuscripts.
One of the things that we see all the time is, well, now it's really common, right?
People are developing services that can use GPT-3 or ChatGPT, or GPT-4 through ChatGPT
to revise your manuscript.
Well, what are the issues with those?
So our experience putting this together and running a bunch of test manuscripts through
it is that, yes, it is good at clarifying language.
There's a lot of things it can help you with.
It actually caught an error in an equation, which I was pretty darn impressed with.
On the other hand, it also makes stuff up.
And so a bit of a challenge if your idea is that you're just going to use this.
And I think, you know, I use this as an example because it's really trivial.
You can try it out yourself and see how it works, and you can get these examples yourself.
The same things are going to be true when we use this in medical context, so we need
to think about them.
I think thinking about them and trying them and experimenting in a low-risk environment
before we move to a high-risk environment is usually a good idea.
So what are the principles that we've kind of come up with as we think about this?
So first, we really do aim for kind of an augmentation, not replacement.
And what that means is, you know, when we apply this to manuscripts and we try to get
it to improve it, you know, we actually applied it to the manuscript about the tool.
And when we did that, it made up this thing that we had done that we had fine-tuned the
model on manuscripts of a similar type.
Yeah, you should absolutely fine-tune the model on manuscripts of a similar type.
Makes a ton of sense.
We didn't do it.
You probably shouldn't report that you did it in the manuscript.
So we're really thinking like, you know, okay, this is not like you're going to plug it in,
you're going to be done.
It's really, you need to design it around kind of an augmentation capability.
You've got to carefully consider your use cases.
You know, if it's easy to take the output, it's hard to compare.
It's probably not good, right?
Because you're creating the opportunity for a mistake that you don't need to create.
We really like to start with these kind of simple solutions and approaches and layer
complexity only as needed.
So in this case, you know, we start with some pretty simple prompts and then have the ability
to add complexity.
But usually we just kind of try to keep it relatively basic and simple.
The workflow is simple.
You can proof of concept it out really quickly.
And the most important thing is preserving attribution.
Like where did the content come from?
If you're thinking about this in a clinical setting, you know, what was provided and when?
And you know, did it come from an AI or a human first?
Because that's really going to matter as you're thinking about evaluating these workflows.
In academic writing, I think it's going to, you're going to want to keep track of whether
something came from an AI based system or if you wrote it.
I think this is, more and more journals are starting to require this.
It's going to be important.
But I just think like these are key principles that I would recommend keeping in mind.
And then finally, I just want to give you an idea of what the environment is like about
at Colorado.
Because some of you may one day look for future jobs and I figure you should know something
about us.
We're not at Boulder.
We're at the Anschutz Medical Campus, which is kind of between the airport and the Denver
airport and Denver itself.
We are a major academic medical center.
And like I said, we're not at Boulder, which is the thing that people most frequently get
confused about.
On July 1st of last year, we actually launched a new department of biomedical informatics.
And you know, we're trying to hire and put together a faculty that are focused on this
idea of kind of making serendipity routine, like how do you surface the right information
at the right time.
Our 30, we're now at 31 faculty, we have a new person starting in May, that will get
us to 32 faculty, have about $65 million in extramural research, just for faculty who
are PIs, on which faculty in the department are PIs, there's a lot of additional collaborative
funding that's not included in this.
We have expertise kind of across the spectrum from precision medicine, through kind of physiological
modeling, we have folks who think about human computer interaction, because if you want
to deploy this stuff in the clinic, you should really think about how humans are going to
interact with it through kind of electrical engineering, medical imaging and AI.
So there's a lot of faculty working in this area.
This I just collected some stuff from early last year.
And that just sort of like, okay, when our faculty mentioned in the press, so there's
stuff in MIT technology review nature, LeMond, Deutschland, I can't remember whatever the
German public radio station is.
So you know, you have a bunch of internationally renowned experts who are at Anschutz, we don't
happen to be at Boulder.
You know, to me, it's like the difference between Georgia Tech and Georgia, I feel like
they're different institutions, we should probably occasionally recognize that.
The other thing that sort of we focused on when we were creating the department, if you
read the sociology literature from the 80s, which I suspect all of you do on a regular
basis, there's this article that I actually think you should read from the sociology literature
from the 80s called the mundanity of excellence.
So this is someone who essentially studied swimmers at many different levels and asked
what differentiates swimmers at one level from another level.
There's a few different principles that come out, but one of the key ones is that excellence
requires qualitative differentiation.
And what I mean by that is, you know, you're not going to move up a level in swimming competitions
by swimming to extra labs.
That's not how it works.
What you're going to do is you're going to focus on your form, you're going to, you know,
you're going to approach the sport differently, you're going to focus on getting rest the
night before the meet, like that's the stuff that people do at higher levels that they
don't do at lower levels.
And as we think about a department, we had to ask like, what's our, okay, what's our
qualitative differentiator?
How are we not just like another biomedical informatics department that just happens to
have more money or something, right?
Like that's not, that's not a real differentiator.
And so what we thought about was creating promotion and tenure guidelines that have,
that are focused on real world impact.
So one of our bullet points in our departmental sort of idea of impact, there is a bullet
point that includes publication.
It's possible, you can do it, we can care about it.
But there's also technology development that gets deployed locally, nationally or internationally.
Software shows up, changes in policy because of your work.
All of that is included in and counts for impact.
Now, probably not all of you will look for tenure track faculty positions in our department.
But if you were to come train or send folks to train with us, I think it's important to
know like that filters down, right?
If that's how faculty are evaluated, that filters all the way down.
So there's an emphasis on real world impact that we have that I think can be our kind
of qualitative differentiator.
And I'll just say, we have a really good training environment.
So we have strong connections with UC Health.
So I told you earlier about one of the UC Health programs that we work closely with
them on.
And Children's Colorado, which is a nationally renowned pediatric cancer hospital, not pediatric
hospital.
I know the pediatric cancer people work in that space.
So we have those tight connections.
If you're interested in seeing your work translate to care, we have, if you're interested in
using genetics to guide care, I think we have one of the best programs in the country
through CCPM.
We have a diverse and internationally recognized faculty.
One of the things that's sometimes a little bit odd for folks at, you know, our tenure
track faculty in DBMI are actually majority women, which I think is uncommon at, in, in
our field.
And then if you like the climate and you, it's a little bit humid here.
We don't have that level of humidity, but we do have more hours of sun per year than
Miami and San Diego.
So if you're interested in the environment around you, we've got that.
And then we've got abundant outdoor activities.
This is one example of the programs that we have.
So this is our computational science PhD program.
There's also a postdoc training grant associated with the same thing.
So if you're interested in this type of thing, feel free to look us up.
You can always drop me an email and I can try to connect you with folks too.
And then with that, I just want to thank the people who make this possible.
So the members of the lab, we really have a kind of robust culture in the lab of sort
of sharing the work that's happening and kind of thinking through each other's projects
in ways that are really helpful.
We also do code review.
So people really pitch out, pitch in together, the department of biomedical informatics and
my leadership team, and then the folks in CCPM, since I shared some of that work, and
then the folks who give us money, I'd be happy to take whatever questions you have.
For the radiology, XAI explainability, did they end up using my grad cam as like how
they liberated the convolutional layer for the confluence?
Yeah.
I don't remember what strategy they used.
And I also don't remember, you know, the saliency map.
I think it's a saliency map, but I'm not 100% sure.
Yeah, there's a, so John posted that first as a blog post, there's now like a PLOS medicine
paper, I think.
Yeah.
I think I probably, yeah.
And I wrote this when it was the blog post and not when it was PLOS medicine paper, which
is what I'd look at.
Yeah.
So with the strange like explainability maps, did that happen even with like augmentations
that would rotate or like zoom in, zoom out?
Like was that with that, it still happened or with a train without that?
Because like, I was thinking like assume in augmentation might solve that bottom band
problem.
Yeah.
So I was wondering if that still.
I'm guessing, so this is Andrew Ng's stuff.
This was the one that he was criticizing.
I think this was just chest x-rays and I don't think they, I don't remember them doing at
least like a patch-based augmentation or anything like that.
Yeah.
And I would say now some of the techniques that are more sophisticated are likely to
control for some of that.
I mean, the other thing you could do is you can also just like do some adversarial training
around the location of the scanner.
The challenge with that is you need to know to do it and to know to do it, you have to
like have someone who's an expert probe your data.
And I think sometimes when we come to things from a computer science perspective, I do
think sometimes we get really excited that something is working and especially if it's
working as well as a human and maybe we get a little bit ahead of ourselves and aren't
skeptical enough about our own results.
So with the pharmacogenomics, the alert system that you pointed out.
So how often do you get sort of false alerts, right?
So because sometimes you can get an alert that a physician may not be really interested
in or think is valid, right?
Yeah.
So we designed this pretty carefully.
So we could bump up our alert number by just whether or not someone's getting a relevant
prescription, fire the alert.
That'd be great for our metrics.
On the other hand, not terribly useful for care and people would learn to ignore it.
So we're pretty focused.
So most of the alerts are non-interruptive.
So the idea is an 80-20 rule.
So only 20% of the alerts should be interruptive, 80% should be non-interruptive.
And because this isn't based on a predictive model, it's pretty straightforward to make
sure it fires largely at times when it's relevant.
So restricting kind of the clinic in which you can fire and that sort of stuff.
However, one of the really nice things about UCHealth, so I'll go back on my advertising
pitch for why you should come to Colorado and work at Colorado if this is something
you're interested in, UCHealth thought about this in advance.
So years ago, they built a virtual health center.
And if you want to look it up, you can look up the UCHealth virtual health center.
The guy who, to my understanding, put this together and sort of was visionary behind
it is a guy named Rich Zane, who's our chief innovation officer through the hospital.
And what they did there is they have nurses and clinicians who work offsite, but who are
available to look at these types of systems before they flow to people who are onsite
providing care.
And where this became really useful, so is anyone aware of kind of the EPIC sepsis model
thing that blew up maybe a year or two ago?
No.
So EPIC is one of the major providers of electronic health record systems.
They have a sepsis model, and that sepsis model is pretty noisy.
It likes to, it alerts probably more frequently than it should, and it misses cases it shouldn't
miss.
So there was a team at CU before my time, led by Tal Bennett, that had evaluated this
model and found that it had some predictive quality, but maybe it wasn't ready.
I want to be careful what I assert here.
It had some predictive quality, but deployed in practice at scale could have created a
lot of unnecessary burden on providers.
Well, what they did, because they have the virtual health center, is they're able to
deploy that model plus others in the virtual health center, have it alert nurses and clinicians
there, and then have them look at it carefully in the virtual health center and only send
the notice over to the folks who are working at the bedside if it's actually going to be
useful.
So a reason that could be good to work at Colorado, if you're interested in kind of
predictive analytics and deploying this stuff in practice, is you can have a model that's
not perfect, right?
It doesn't have to be good enough to hand to a provider at the bedside.
Because of the virtual health center, you can really proof of concept it out there,
improve it, understand how you can improve its predictive quality, and then deploy it
when it's ready.
But you can still get the benefit in the meantime.
So I guess I'd say, yeah, I think our noise level is pretty low on these alerts, but we
do have a system in place for noisier stuff if people want to deploy it.
It's fun to be back in Athens.
Time to go dogs.
I don't know what else I should say, but I'm just excited to be back.
I was really tickled when I got the invite, it was wonderful.