My pleasure to introduce Professor Yang, who joined UGA last semester and as a class chair
of ecology, mathematics, and statistics, but he doesn't have any commitment to
or ecology. So this seminar also serves for his application for the adjunct position with IOB.
So if you're a student and looking for lab, you may want to talk to him. His major research area
is infectious disease, and he is a statistician modeling for infectious disease. As you know,
to understand infectious disease, we need the knowledge in ecology, population genetics,
molecular genetics, to understand evolution of pathogens, and mathematics, you know,
as well as statistics. So it's very hard to find an expert in all of those areas,
and here we go. Professor Yang, so if you're interested in doing research in infectious
disease, you probably want to talk to him. He has a lot of grants. He's already published over 100
papers, and this is, believe me, this is just the first page of his CV. So I cannot read out
all the CVs. It's 19 pages. So he, let's see. Sorry, I'm aging, so I cannot see that. So he
got his PhD in 2004 from Emory, and he did his postdoc at Howard, right, so for the following
year, and then he worked at Brad Hutchinson Cancer Center, and then he moved to University
of Florida, and last semester, he joined again. So today, he's going to talk about epidemiology
and ecology of Middle East Respiratory Syndrome coronavirus.
Okay, good. Thank you, Liang, for this nice introduction and over compliment.
I'm not expert in everything, and I mainly specialize in modeling of infectious disease
transmission, and just started working with Dr. Liu on how to combine the epidemiological part
and the physiological part into the same model so that we can better model the dynamics of
transmission. Today, I'm going to talk about epidemiology and the ecology of MERS-CoV.
If you read the flyer before, I changed my title a little bit. I used to have
transmission as well, but I found myself too many. I had to cut some, so I moved that one out.
So today, we'll only be talking about epidemiology and the ecology.
Hopefully, you will be interested in these topics. So this is during the work with Dr.
Yichun Fang and Wenqiang Shi at Beijing Institute of Microbiology and Epidemiology, as well as Dr.
Anna Zhang at Shandong University. Anna was a business student in my lab at UF.
That's when she was leading this project, part of this project.
Please feel free to stop me anytime if you have any questions.
So some background about the disease and the pathogen as well.
You're probably quite familiar with this disease because of the pandemic of SARS-CoV-2.
MERS is a respiratory infection disease first found in the kingdom of Saudi Arabia.
As of January this year, there were a total of 27 countries that have reported about 2,600
lab-confirmed cases, together with 935 deaths. So that's a pretty good number.
That has reported about 2,600 lab-confirmed cases, together with 935 deaths. So that's a
pretty high case fatality rate. We use the CMR of about 36%.
Luckily, human-to-human transmission is pretty rare, and many occurred in healthcare settings
and households. And in healthcare settings, it's pretty much patients who are immune-compromised.
So that's why they are at high risk of transmission.
And the zoonotic infection is mainly driven by exposure to the dummy debris,
wire droplets, fomites, and consumption of some raw products of this animal, such as milk.
And people also suspect the use of chemical urine as a traditional medicine is another
transmission route. And given that there has been no effective treatment or vaccine yet,
so people are very concerned about the potential of this virus causing another global pandemic
if it's fully adapted itself to the human population. And in 2018, WHO incorporated MERS
into its research and development blueprint, which lists a variety of disease pathogens
that people will spend more time developing vaccines toward those pathogens.
And about the virus itself, it's an RNA virus with a genome about 30 kb long.
And MERS-CoV belongs to the lineage C of the genus beta coronavirus. The famous or infamous
SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2, they belong to the lineage B. And the common code coronaviruses,
OC43 and HKU1, they belong to the lineage K. So they're related, but a little bit distant
from each other. MERS-CoV was phylogenetically classified into clade A and clade B. A includes
the early detected human cases, viruses, and B includes the more contemporary viruses.
But however, this classification was based on a pretty few number of sequences. So we've done
a much more comprehensive work on this, and we'll show that later.
Although the disease was quite new, but circulation of MERS-like coronaviruses
in Africa and the Arabian Peninsula occurred well before 2012.
And a little bit about the immunity background of this virus. The virus used the S1 protein
to bind to two types of host cell surface molecules. One is called the DPP4, and the other
is the well-known alpha-2 or alpha-3 astatic acids. And it replicates mainly in the nasal
epithelium of dromedaries, but only in the lower respiratory tract of humans. So that's probably
why it's so highly transmissible among the dromedaries, but not so much among human beings.
All right, so that's enough for the background. Let me get into the needs.
We'll try to identify determinants for case fatality rate and also characterize the spatial
division pattern of the disease. And we want to also look at evolution and migration history
of the virus. Finally, we'll provide some more comprehensive picture about the ecology of the
virus. And we'll also look at the evolution and migration history of the virus, and we'll also
picture about the ecology of the virus and associated socio-environmental drivers.
But this talk has two parts. The first two are part one, and this is part two.
So in this slide, I talk about the data sources.
We first collected data on all confirmed human cases, and there are three major sources for that.
We looked at the official reports of WHO. Now, WHO does not provide the line list it used to.
So we were lucky. At that time, we got a line list. And the Food and Agriculture Organization
of the United Nations, as well as the health departments of affected countries.
So we collected demographic data whenever it's available, and the dates of
critical events, like the onset, hospitalization, and the lab confirmation.
The most important one is to explore your history, but it's very simple. It's just whether
the case has had a history of exposure to animal production or other confirmed patient.
And we validate this data via literature research. We also collected a bunch of socio-environmental
variables, which are listed here, and we'll utilize them, especially using, for example,
meteorological data and land cover data for ecology study. The gene sequence data were
downloaded from our gene bank, and we used data up to the June of 2020, and that's also
the time upper limit for the case data we downloaded.
This is an epidemic curve actually provided in the WHO report, and it only listed cases
in the eastern Mediterranean region. It's not for the whole world, but because we want to
check the seasonality, so we decided to focus on the endemic in the zoonotic region instead of the
local region. And it covers from June 2012 to January 2023. This is more comprehensive than
the data that we used. We used up to June of 2020, but luckily there weren't many cases after that.
I mentioned it was first discovered in September 2012, but you can see here,
actually the earliest case shown here can be traced back to early
2012, so there could be some cases retrospectively identified.
All right. Majority of these cases from Saudi Arabia. That's understandable. Everyone knows that.
And we see a huge peak in 2014 and some subsequent large outbreaks in 2015.
And you can also see there were about two peaks per year and sometimes three peaks
right. One in the early spring and the other one probably in the late summer or early fall.
And the early ones in the spring, it's more like an animal exposure in a triggered spinoma.
So here is a summary table of the kind of baseline characteristics of all the
worst cases we included in our study covering this period.
Right. And I colored some of these interesting results.
In Saudi Arabia, it has far more number of cases as well as number of deaths
compared to other countries. And if you look at the CFR, it's also much higher than other regions.
In South Korea, I should say South Korea, sorry for that,
the number of female patients were much higher than other countries.
That's possibly due to, because in Korea, if you know the history of MERS,
there was a big outbreak in, if I remember correctly, it was in 2015.
It's kind of driven by one single imported case. And that patient kind of stimulated large outbreaks
in several hospitals. So it's purely kind of a person-to-person transmission. And in that case,
it doesn't really distinguish between different sexes, right? But for animal exposure, we'll see
later, most of the patients with animal exposure are men. And so that will make some difference.
And in these countries, KSA, UAE, and some other countries, the majority of patients are male.
And South Korea also has a very large percent of hospital-related
patients. And that's exactly because we only had hospital outbreaks in that country.
And the time from disease onset to diagnosis was shortest in South Korea. And that's also
understandable because those were hospital-triggered investigations. They are very efficient, right?
In the United Arab Emirates, we noticed that the age was, the patients were much younger
compared to other countries. And that is probably because of the high proportion of healthcare
workers compared to other countries. And this country also has the highest proportion of
asymptomatic infection. How you identify asymptomatic infection is a very tricky question.
Usually, for syndrome-based surveillance, you only can find symptomatic cases. Because of
this high proportion of healthcare workers, probably they did some regular monitoring
for infection status. And that's how they identified asymptomatic infections.
And this country also has a very long time from disease onset to death. The reason for that
is unknown, but probably related to the management of patient or facility in the hospitals.
So that's for the summary table. Any questions?
Okay. So that's the basic epidemiology. Let's go to more interesting materials.
In this table, we compare the characteristics between cases with animal contact and those without.
About one-fourth of patients were reported animal contact.
So we can see patients with animal contact were much less likely to be female
compared to this proportion. And they were older. And the case fatality rate was much higher.
But we need to be very careful for interpreting this much higher case fatality rate. Because
this animal contact, we'll see later, it's confounded with other factors like age,
like baseline chronic conditions. If we really want to assess animal contact
effect on case fatality rate, we need to adjust for those confounders.
It's also less likely to be asymptomatic. But that, again, is a question mark. That probably
does not give you any epidemiological... It doesn't describe epidemiology in that regard
faithfully. Because for people with animal contact, many of them probably asymptomatic,
asymptomatic, and they were not captured by this learning system.
And they had much higher proportion of underlying conditions, as I mentioned before.
So they're probably at higher risk to death. And they generally had a much longer time from
the disease onset to diagnosis. So we'll find later. So that will also probably increase the
fatality rate. But for some reason, a slightly longer time from disease onset to death,
which we don't quite understand, probably related to some immunology issues.
If we look at the proportion of animal contact, a patient with animal contact,
across the years, now these proportions are the low proportions.
Even though we had fewer and fewer cases over the years, we actually see a different story
for this proportion of animal contact. It increases up to 2018, and then they kind of
plateaued. And it's not decreasing yet. I'm not sure about the most recent years.
The data is not available yet.
So this figure shows the spatial distribution of human MERS cases in the whole globe.
We categorize the countries into four categories. The first two categories
corresponds to the colors of, I would say, maybe I can call that pink, and a little bit of purple.
Those countries had zoonotic transmissions, basically animal exposure. The pink ones
reported a human-to-human transmission, and the purple one did not report,
or at least did not find concrete evidence for human-to-human transmission.
And if you look at this map, only Kuwait is the country colored with purple.
And it doesn't really mean it did not have human-to-human transmission. I'll explain why.
The other two categories are the countries with many important infections,
so they're colored with yellow or brown. The yellow indicates there was human-to-human
transmission following the importation. And the brown ones, I believe,
are the ones without subsequent human-to-human. Oh no, sorry, it's reversed. The yellow ones,
did not have human-to-human transmission, but the brown ones had this type of incidence.
All right, and for each country with reported cases, we impose a bar chart like this,
and the size of the bar indicates number of cases, and then the colors indicate
animal contact history. The red indicates the proportion of patients with animal contact.
And if you look at Kuwait, it's basically red and green. Green simply means unknown,
right? So whether there were human-to-human transmission, we don't know, just not confirmed.
And interestingly, Qatar is the country with the highest proportion of animal contact,
followed by ASA, UAE, and Oman. Some small countries like these,
Bahrain has too few cases, so I wouldn't make any conclusion for that.
Some European countries also reported patients with animal contact, as well as here in Southeast
Asia. But these people most likely already had animal contact before they entered
those countries. So to look at what factors contributed to the risk of death,
so we performed a standard logistic regression. For all the variables that we have that we think
are related, we throw them into the model, we perform the univariable analysis and the
multivariable analysis, and all these factors we throw in are significant in both univariable and
multivariable analysis. These are strong predictors for case fatality. Let's just go ahead with the
multivariable analysis. Don't look at the age, sex, and animal contact yet, because we have
interaction terms in the model. And these numbers, like this high number, 10.52, does not represent a
marginal effect of age group. It does not. It's just specific to one particular subgroup, and I'll talk
about that later. So let's just look at the effects of, say, a healthcare worker, as much lower risk
of death. And underlying condition, well, that's a more than three-fold increase in the risk of death.
OTC stands for the time from onset to confirmation, it's basically diagnosis, right? Then
this has also a significant result. A longer time from onset to confirmation
increases the risk of death. And if we compare the years, we divide the time into three segments,
and this early phase, this middle phase with large outbreaks, and this later phase with very few cases.
And all compared to the early years, we can see a jump in the risk of death. That's probably,
at least partly due to the constrained, exhausted healthcare facilities, because the large number
of patients. And in the later years, we see a slightly decrease in the risk of death,
possibly related to improved patient management, and also the much fewer number of patients.
So we left out the most three interesting factors, age, sex, and animal contact. So let's get into those.
In this table, we look at age effect, conditioning on sex and animal contact.
Let's focus on the adjusted odd ratio directly. These are all pretty big numbers,
these are all pretty big numbers, all significant. But let's do some comparison.
Let's first compare the results between female and male, right?
But you have to condition on the same contact history, right? So with contact history, with
animal contact history, if you compare female with male, and then without contact history, female with
female with male, right? Without actually comparing this guy, this guy with that guy.
So basically, this is bigger than that, and this is bigger than that. So within females,
age effect is more prominent, regardless of animal contact history.
Age effect is basically comparing the older age to the younger age.
And this number shows in the previous table, it's just for this particular subset of population.
So age is the most prominent driver for the risk of death. And that's not affected by
by either sex or, no, it is affected by sex, right? In female, it's more prominent.
And it's not that affected, it is also affected by animal contact. Let's compare the animal contact history.
So if you look at, just compare with to without, with to without, and with to without,
you can see without animal contact, age effect is more prominent, regardless of the underlying sex.
So that's quite interesting. Why is that? Why is that?
Remember, males, many of them were actually farm workers, they had animal exposure. So
we can reasonably speculate that these patients were constantly challenged by the virus.
Okay, probably that's a buildup of immunity towards this virus.
So after adjusting for the underlying conditions, and adjusted for the
yeah, adjusted for underlying conditions and some other risk factors,
we can see the difference in the age group between people with, without animal contact.
With animal contact, the age effect is not that prominent, but without, it is very prominent.
And most of the animal workers, they were older than younger. So that's for age effect.
Let's look at the effect of gender.
We don't see many strong signals. The only statistically significant result is within
the subgroup of male, the older patients without animal contact.
And male has a much higher risk of death than female.
However, we also noticed that this effect is, you know, has some kind of a marginal signal here.
And it is in the opposite direction compared to what we see here.
And this subgroup is for the younger, no, for the older patients with animal contact.
So that's, that's also quite interesting. For younger patients without animal contact,
male has much higher risk of death. But within older patients with animal contact,
male has actually lower risk of death.
And that again, give us a difficult question to answer, why is that?
However, we should also notice that within the category of older patients with animal contact
and female, we have small number. So that's why this is not statistically significant.
So that could be just due to random noise. So maybe we should not over-interpret this 0.45.
You actually use a mouse because I don't think, and this is my laser point, that means online.
You cannot see that? You actually use mouse.
Yeah, let me use mouse. I apologize to the online audience.
All right, now finally, let's look at the effect of animal contact conditioning on sex and age group.
Now, here, let's just focus on the significant results. The most significant result is this guy.
That's ignored, unknown category, just to focus on what we've done.
Right, so within the subgroup of female patients and younger female patients,
we see a huge increased risk of death for patients with animal contact.
Remember, these are female patients. Most animal workers were males.
So females, if they had animal contact, it's probably more likely to be a vocational contact,
not a professional contact. So that means you may not have to build up immunity against this virus.
Right, so once you had contact with animal and got infected, then it's probably a high risk of
death. And this virus just jumped from animal to human, has not been adapted much to the human
immune system. But if you look at the subgroup of male patients, the older male patients,
if you look at with, without animal contact, you see a huge reduction in the risk of death.
And most of these male patients with animal contact, especially the older ones,
they were actually animal workers. They had probably long exposure to the virus.
Any questions? A lot of information here, difficult to digest in such a short time.
Oh, I already see people have put in chat. Okay, let's move on. So those were for the
risk factors for death. Now let's look at the spatial diffusion pattern.
So what we did here is we look at the time from the first case overall to the first case
in each local district. That's the first time the local district was invaded by this virus.
With this time as my outcome, I did some, you know, spatial smoothing to construct this contour
plot. And this contour plot can tell me the diffusion pattern. And the wider gap between the
two contours indicates, let me put it this way, because the gap between each contour plot is
kind of fixed for the time interval, 200 days. And a wider gap means a longer spatial distance.
So that means a faster spread, right? The first case, first case was here in a city
called Bisho, somewhere in south, in western KSA. And this star marks the first patient that
sparked a outbreak, human patient cluster. So this Bisho is kind of in the central
point of these contour plots. And in the more recent times, we can see actually faster spreading
and the direction was towards Oman and somewhere of UAE.
Right. But that's a characteristic of this plot. We did not show the uncertainty, right?
So probably here you have fewer data, then uncertainty could be high. And whether the
conclusion that they have fastest spreading, maybe just a noise. But however, if you look
at this figure, this map here, let me use mouse again. If you look at the map in the right panel,
you can see in this corner, we still have a bunch of cases. So those cases will inform
the construction of this contour plot. So the signal here in this corner should be reliable.
Right. And you can also notice that we overlay this map with the transportation network.
The white, black lines indicate railway and these gray lines indicate the major roads.
And you can see a pretty good overlap of the cases with this transportation network.
And that's what we're going to show in another model fitting.
So here we perform the survival analysis. Again, the outcome is a time from the first
ever reported worst case to the first importation of case into each district.
The so-called district here, it is a second level administrative unit in most countries,
except for KSA. Because KSA is relatively big. So in case A, we use county, which is a third level
administrative area. And we fit this survival model, trying to look at, this is not an
ecological model. It's just to try to look at what might have contributed to
the invasion of the virus into these different spatial units. Right. Again,
that's just a look at the multivariable analysis. And here we are estimating hazard ratio.
The most prominent hazard ratio is related to the intersection with the main road.
So after that, it was elevation, the higher elevation, the higher hazard ratio.
And also intersection with railway, it more than doubled the hazard of invasion.
And interestingly, the coverage of cropland, it seems to deter the spread, which is also
understandable. These bio variables, they are meteorological variables. And I listed the
interpretations here. Bio one is simply the annual average temperature. And the bio two is the
average diurnal range of temperature, which is simply is kind of the average.
The difference between the maximum temperature and a minimum temperature within each month,
then you take an average. It reflects the variation over time, but within each month.
So these two had shown some significant results, increasing the higher temperature or the higher
mortality, increase the hazard of invasion.
Finally, comes down to the something that may be interesting.
So we collected the whole genome sequence from GenBank. And we analyzed these sequences using
the toolkits provided by Nextstrain. The sequences were aligned using MAFFT, what do you call it?
MAFFT? MAFFT. And the alignment was trained to a reference genome in GenBank. And we constructed
the phylogenetic tree using the maximum likelihood approach implemented in the IQ tree software.
And for the final geographic analysis, we use the tree time to estimate, you know,
the location and host time of those internal nerves. And initial analysis shown on the left
panel suggested that
the sequences from bats, I think by these pink leaf nodes, and hedgehog,
not by the yellow leaf nodes, they separated kind of distant from the main clades of sequences
formed by humans and camels, as well as a single strain from a llama, I think, the animal.
It is hiding here.
And we, so then we just exclude all the sequences of bats and hedgehogs and only focus on the
human and the camel genes.
So on the right hand panel, you can see we had several clusters for human and camel genes.
We have five clusters. The largest cluster is called C5, which contains majority of the sequences.
And you can see the mixture of human and camel sequences throughout the tree, except for the
most recent ones, where I think this was more like a sampling using, rather than a
systematic pattern. So this mixture of human-camel sequences
suggests that there were probably constant importation of sphere number from camel to human.
Now, this figure shows the phylogeny in a much better way because we can we can
time here, right? So although the human and camel sequences are mixed together,
but if you look at the samples collected after 2016,
the human genes are quite distant from the camel genes, right?
And the common ancestor was dated around 2007, and the posterior probability for the host being
camel, human, kind of 50-50. We later did a sensitivity analysis. We downsampled the human
sequences because there's just too many of them. And then the camel will have a 99%
for the posterior probability being the common ancestor.
We also tried to associate case fatality rate with sequences.
So what we did is we look at, we kind of divide the spatial temporal
range into several chunks and calculate the case fatality rate within each chunk.
And then we look at the individual sequences and associate them with the case fatality rate
in that chunk, the location and the time. And then we, for each sequence, we have a bar
with a color indicating the underlying case fatality rate in that space time chunk.
And then we average for each cluster to compare the potential difference in case fatality rate
between clusters. If you compare C5 to other clusters, C1 to C4, you cannot really see much
difference between the two. Actually, there's only 1% difference in case fatality rate there,
only 1%. But it is significant, probably because of the sample size, but we cannot
fully interpret that. If you compare only the sub-clade C5.1 with C1 to C4, we actually see
a 4% difference, which is not true. So that means the more recent clade is probably more lethal.
We also associated the incidence rate with sequences, but we cannot see much signal there,
so I'm going to ignore that. Oh, there's another thing I want to share. Okay, so we,
remember, we performed some phylogeographic analysis. So let's take a look at a movie.
Hopefully, this movie will show. Let's see.
Just a copy-paste.
Oh, we're not. We should go back to the window mode, and just copy-paste this one.
Let's see if we can do it.
Let's see if it works or not.
Oh, I have to move it to...
Oh, I have to stop sharing.
Oh, I see, I see. Yeah, okay.
Let me click on it here.
I want to see that geographic location.
I'm scrolling down, maybe.
Scrolling down.
All right, yes, and then replay.
I'm sorry for this problem, but it's kind of out of my control.
Where is play?
Just click play.
Okay, yeah, now let's take a look.
Yeah, it's almost finished. All right, good.
Good, okay.
Now, let me... Oh, still, that's correct to share a screen, right?
Right, okay.
Now, some highlights for that movie, right?
The top three most likely locations for the common access route were three cities, Riyadh of KSA and now Delta region, which is in Egypt and Jordan.
The possibilities are 31%, 17% and 12% respectively.
And Riyadh appears to be the major source of exporting infections, both locally and internationally.
And it is the common ancestor node of subclades C3, C4 and C5 for 99% of time.
Okay, and the early exportation to Egypt and Jordan occurred well before 2010.
And the circulation of the MERS-CoV among camels in East Africa possibly started also before 2010.
The virus migrated from Egypt to Ethiopia during 2011-2013, and subsequently to Kenya during 2014-2017.
And that's partially supported by a zoological study conducted in Egypt in 2013, where they also sampled animals from Kenya and found nothing.
The intense migration from Riyadh towards local cities in KSA, as well as Abu Dhabi in UAE, started around the 1970s, which matches our knowledge.
And Abu Dhabi joined Riyadh as the second home for exporting the virus, both locally and internationally. So that's quite early.
And the model also captures the opportunistic exportation to the US as well as to the US.
So we also did some kind of detection of
positive selection across proteins and the sites. Remember in the previous slide, see here.
Now I'm notating here branch A and branch B. Branch A is kind of separating
the hedgehog sequences from the rest, and branch B is separating hedgehog and
bat sequences from human and camel sequences. So we performed the
positive selection analysis along these two branches.
Okay, the first three rows of branch A, we identified three proteins, the non-structural three, nucleoprotein, and this 1AB polyprotein is, I believe, it's from the open reading form 1.
I may be wrong, but that's my impression. And we identified the signs
with positive selection. Only in this 1AB polyprotein, not in the other two. Along the branch B, we identified these two proteins, including the spike protein.
For the branch A, we did not detect the spike protein for any positive selection.
And also for the spike protein, we identified these sides to be under high
pressure for positive selection. And the three ones marked by red, those are newly found. They did not appear in the literature.
And we all know spike protein is the one that most interacts with animal cells.
How much time do I have?
It's already...
Yeah, already 10 seconds.
Okay, okay. Then I'll probably ignore the ecology part. For the ecology part, I can just mention some main findings.
What we did here is we used several machine learning approaches like post-signal regression tree,
supported by commission, and random forest to learn the ecology of the spike protein.
And then we build a meta-learner on top of this. It will give us another round of prediction, and it turns out that the ensemble machine, which is a meta-learner,
outperforms the three base models. Not by much, but a little bit. If you look at the AUC, if you look at the accuracy, as well as F1 score and compound,
not really a good performance in terms of sensitivity, but sensitivity here is a little bit deceptive because we have very few positive cases.
This model is based on about 100 positive districts with confirmed cases, and about 400
districts without any detection.
And we did identify... Let me see. We did identify the most prominent risk driver for ecology of MERS-CoV. It's actually something called the coverage of bare land.
Bare land, that's very, very difficult to define. Basically, a land without many, you know, vegetation, trees, like that, right?
But we also adjusted for camel density here. Camel density is picked up by the model,
but not as a very prominent driver. So we want to control the camel density. Then it's bare land,
in addition to camel, it may also contain other animal hosts that we have not discovered yet.
Okay, so let me just draw some conclusions on the epithelium model.
So we observed that the cases with animal contact
tend to be older, more likely to be male, symptomatic, and also having underlying conditions. Even though by our
logistic model with interactions, we kind of see that once you adjust your model,
underlying conditions, adjusting for age and gender, animal contact actually does not always increase the risk of death.
Remember, in the older population, and male, it actually decreases the risk of death.
But overall, for those older males who are farm workers, animal workers, because they had underlying conditions, and they were old,
overall, they do have a higher risk of death.
So we should consider promoting some preventive measures, like an educational campaign or personal protection equipment for those workers.
But overall, for those older males who are farm workers, animal workers, because they had underlying conditions, and they were old,
overall, they do have a higher risk of death. And we need to pay attention to that.
So we should consider promoting some preventive measures, like an educational campaign or personal protection equipment for those workers.
And animal-to-human transmission events mainly occurred between January and March,
and human-to-human transmission occurred later in summer.
So that suggests the importance of blocking the spillover from animal to human in the early spring.
And also mentioning, we found sample sequences after 2014, many human sequences, and then camel becomes the host for the root ancestor with a very high possibility.
And we also found Abu Dhabi of UAE is a hub for international exportation of this virus.
So this virus, probably, we should recommend some kind of screening procedure for infected travelers.
And the novel amino acids positions that we found on spike protein associated with public selection,
those can be potential pockets for the spread of this virus.
So we should consider promoting some preventive measures, like an educational campaign or personal protection equipment for those workers.
And the novel amino acids positions that we found on spike protein associated with public selection,
those can be potential pockets for development of future antiviral vaccines against this virus.
So that's all for that material.
And the NP paper is published in this journal, and the ecology paper is published in this journal.
Thank you very much. Any questions, you're welcome.
Yes, please. I'm really interested about the phylogeny. Can you go back to the figure four or five?
Yeah, that's the one. So, since after 2016, it's really interesting, like, human birds and
camels are pretty much distinct. Do you think it's because the sampling bios of the camel,
or do you believe there's somehow a low level circulation of human population?
That's a good question. I don't have the answer. My intuition is sampling virus is at least a contributing factor.
It's hard to imagine, because this virus is endemic in camels. It's hard to imagine it's gone. I don't think it's gone.
So, Ryan in the chat would like to know what type of models make up your own sample.
Oh, so the base models are a random forest, boosted regression tree, and
support vector machine. And then on top of that, the meta-learner is actually XGBoost.
Does that answer your question?
Yes, thank you.
Yes, so it seems like this is a fairly small tree. Why did you end up choosing
using the Nextstrain pipeline as opposed to a different tree building pipeline?
It was not my decision. My intuition would always try maybe like a beast first.
However, I wouldn't say it's a small data set either, because we have, I think, about 500 sequences together.
A beast may need some time to run. And another nice thing about the Nextstrain is that it provides
all sorts of tools together for you to use, and with this nice movie. So I think that's
probably the only reason why we chose Nextstrain. But I think definitely you can try a beast as well,
especially for the geographic analysis.
Could you tell us more about surveillance or genome sequencing of camel or
reservoir species? I think that's really important because it can give us a
good background about circulation in these reservoirs and spillover between them.
I'm not quite sure whether there is a systematic surveillance system for animals.
Actually, in terms of animal hosts, although at least the bats and hedgehogs here
if you look into the literature, it's still kind of debatable, right? We all have common sense.
Bats is the natural reservoir for all types of coronaviruses, including MERS,
MERS-CoV. But as a matter of fact, so far people have only found, to my knowledge,
kind of similar gene segments in the virus as in the form of bats.
That's not considered some very solid evidence by many of our biologists and immunologists.
Yeah, I know less about the hedgehogs, so I cannot say much about that.
So the primary animal host that's solidly convincing people is camels,
scum, gondolins. And we should do surveillance.
I have a question about student training because you're applying for adjunct
faculty position here. So what kind, what type of students would you expect working in your lab,
or how would you train bioinformatics students? In terms of bioinformatics itself,
I need a partner like Dr. Liu. Myself, no, I cannot train you. I'm very interested in this
field, but myself, I need to be trained as well. But my vision is that, you know,
we don't have this vision. We want to combine biological data, gene sequence data. So far,
we're only talking about the pathogen sequence, right? It could be human sequence as well,
but that's a long shot. And also like human movement data, all together to inform us about
the transmission dynamics. And that's also very important to understand how the virus is going to
evolve in terms of its transmissibility, pathogenicity, and so on.
So far, there have been some efforts in this kind of joint modeling in the past 10 years, but
it's still under investigated. It's still a very promising direction. So anybody with interest in
both bioinformatics and statistics and computational methods are welcome to join this effort.
Yeah, sure. It says elevation was insignificant in the univariable analysis. Why was it included
in the multivariable and into that mix? Good question. Let me check.
Elevation. That's for the survival analysis, is that? Yes.
Yeah.
Oh, this is kind of more like a statistical philosophy question,
right? Because here, we did not explore the potential interactions explicitly.
So there could be interactions among these factors. And in the univariable analysis,
it's not significant. Actually, the p-value is very close to one, but that does not mean
it's not having an interaction. Or it could be a confounder. Because if you look at the
coverage of a bare land with elevation, there is some correlation there.
Right? Not very high, not super high, but there is some substantial correlation there.
So we cannot just rule it out. In the multivariable model, we did not just leave
out those non-significant in the multivariate model. We actually add them back one by one
to check whether they're going to become significant after adjusting for other factors.
So that's the reason.
Thank you. All right. If there's no questions, let's send Professor Gao.
Yeah, I think I set it up. I know I have to clean up, so I won't be there.
All right. I think that's something else.
Yeah. Should I go?
You can just show up. I'll show up at the booth, I guess.